Sentinels were placed at all the approaches to the farm.
In addition, four pigeons were sent to Foxwood with a conciliatory message,
which it was hoped might reestablish good relations with Pilkington.
The very next morning, the attack came.
The animals were at breakfast when the lookouts came racing in with the news
that Frederick and his followers had already come through the five-barred gate.
Boldly enough, the animals sallied forth to meet them, but this time they did not
have the easy victory that they had had in the Battle of the Cowshed.
There were 15 men with half a dozen guns between them, and they opened fire as
soon as they got within 50 yards.
The animals could not face the terrible explosions and the stinging pellets, and
in spite of the efforts of Napoleon and Boxer to rally them, they were soon driven back.
A number of them were already wounded.
They took refuge in the farm buildings and peeped cautiously out from chinks and knotholes.
The whole of the big pasture, including the windmill, was in the hands of the enemy.
For the moment, even Napoleon seemed at a loss.
He paced up and down without a word, his tail rigid and twitching.
Wistful glances were sent in the direction of Foxwood.
If Pilkington and his men would help them, the day might yet be won.
But at this moment, the four pigeons who had been sent out on the day before returned.
One of them bearing a scrap of paper from Pilkington.
On it was penciled the words, >> "Serves you right."
>> Meanwhile, Frederick and his men had halted about the windmill.
The animals watched them and a murmur of dismay went round.
Two of the men had produced a crowbar and a sledgehammer.
They were going to knock the windmill down.
>> "Impossible! We have built the walls far too thick for that. They could not knock
it down in a week. Courage, comrades."
>> But Benjamin was watching the movements of the men intently.
The two with the hammer and the crowbar were drilling a hole near the base of the windmill.
Slowly and with an air almost of amusement, Benjamin nodded his long muzzle.
>> "I thought so.
Do you not see what they are doing?
In another moment, they are going to pack blasting powder into that hole."
>> Terrified, the animals waited.
It was impossible now to venture out of the shelter of the buildings.
After a few minutes, the men were seen to be running in all directions.
Then, there was a deafening roar.
The pigeons swirled into the air and all the animals, except Napoleon, flung
themselves flat on their bellies and and hid their faces.
When they got up again, a huge cloud of black smoke was hanging where the windmill had been.
Slowly, the breeze drifted it away.
The windmill had ceased to exist.
At this sight, the animals' courage returned to them.
The fear and despair they had felt a moment earlier were drowned in their
rage against this vile, contemptible act.
A mighty cry for vengeance went up, and without waiting for further orders, they
charged forth in a body and made straight for the enemy.
This time, they did not heed the cruel pellets that swept over them like hail.
It was a savage, bitter battle.
The men fired again and again, and when the animals got to close quarters,
lashed out with their sticks and their heavy boots.
A cow, three sheep, and two geese were killed, and nearly everyone was wounded.
Even Napoleon, who was directing operations from the rear, had the tip of
his tail chipped by a pellet.
But the men did not go unscathed, either.
Three of them had their heads broken by blows from Boxer's hooves. Another was
gored in the belly by a cow's horn.
Another had his trousers nearly torn off by Jessie and Bluebell.
And when the nine dogs of Napoleon's own bodyguard, whom he had instructed to
make a detour under cover of the hedge, suddenly appeared on the men's flank,
baying ferociously, panic overtook them.
They saw that they were in danger of being surrounded.
Frederick shouted to his men to get out while the going was good, and the next
moment, the cowardly enemy was running for dear life.
The animals chased them right down to the bottom of the field and got in some
last kicks at them as they forced their way through the thorn hedge.
They had won, but they were weary and bleeding.
Slowly they began to limp back towards the farm.
The sight of their dead comrades stretched upon the grass moved some of them to tears.
And for a little while they halted in sorrowful silence at the place where the
windmill had once stood.
Yes, it was gone.
Almost the last trace of their labor was gone.
Even the foundations were partially destroyed.
And in rebuilding it, they could not